Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Plans, Reports, Agreements and Manuals, 1925-1954, 1955, 1959, 1960, 1962-1965, 1966, 1967, 1970, 1972-1975, 1978-1986, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 2000, 2002, 2005, 2008, undated
  - Long Range Plans, 1965, 1967, 1978-1986
    - GSM Long Range Plan 1986, 1985 October (Box 193, Folder 4)
    - GSM Long Range Plan 1987, 1986 October (Box 193, Folder 5)
  - The Man with the Golden Pen Plans, 1967
    - The Man with the Golden Pen Plans and Results, 1967 (Box 193, Folder 6)
      Materials include two The Man with the Golden Pen Plans and Results Books. These books were issued to all field forces with an introductory letter from Senior Vice President and Agency Director Ernest Shell to "plan your work and work your plans." Each book includes work space to record business and self development plans and goals and enables the measurement of progress toward accomplishment.
  - Transportation Management Plans, 1991, 1994, 1995
    - Regulation 15 Plan, 1991 November (Box 193, Folder 7)
    - Rule 1501 First Year Plan, 1994 April, August, September (Box 193, Folder 8-10)
    - Rule 1501 Annual Analysis, 1995 September (Box 193, Folder 11)
  - Reports, 1925-1954, 1962-1965, circa 1975, 1979
    - Comparative Reports, 1925-1954 (Box 193, Folder 12)
    - Secretary's Report on Insurance Activities, 1929 (Box 193, Folder 13)
    - Advance Report of Division of Insurance, 1934 (Box 193, Folder 14)
    - Theft Report, 1946 April 17 (Box 193, Folder 15)
      Materials include a service confirmation letter from Pinkerton's National Detective Agency concerning a vault theft at the GSM Home Office and theft report transcripts from the following employees: Helen E. Hodge, Barbara Pitts, Amanda Lockett, Anna Rosa Beverly, Helen Blaine, Mary Holmes, Samuel Sockwell, John Prowd and Mr. Leroy Jennings, Contractor for Office Cleaning. Materials also include handwritten theft reports from Assistant to the Controller Helen E. Hodge.
    - Negro Market and Life Insurance Companies reports, 1962-1965 (Box 193, Folder 16)
    - GSM Community Relations Report, circa 1975 (Box 193, Folder 17)
    - GSM Management Field Study Report, 1979 (Box 194, Folder 1)
  - Agreements, 1925, 1948, 1949, 1954, 1959, 1962, 1966, 1970, 1992, 1994
    - Agent's contract, 1925 (Box 194, Folder 2)
    - Collective Agreement with Agency Club, 1948 (Box 194, Folder 3)
    - Agency Club Agreement, 1949 July (Box 194, Folder 4)
    - Supplemental Agreement, 1954 (Box 194, Folder 5)
    - Agreements, 1959, 1962, 1966, 1994 (Box 194, Folder 6)
      Materials include Agreements between GSM and the Insurance Workers International Union.
    - Cafeteria Agreement, 1970 (Box 194, Folder 7)
    - Account Executive's contract with GSM, 1992 (Box 194, Folder 8)
  - Manuals, 1935, 1941, 1955, 1960, 1963, 1974, 1991, 1993, 1996, undated
    - Agent's Reinstatements, 1935 (Box 194, Folder 9)
    - Premiums and Values, 1941 (Box 194, Folder 10)
    - Special Ordinary Training Kit, 1955 (Box 194, Folder 11)
    - Year to Date Performance Ratings, 1960 (Box 195, Folder 1)
    - Recommended Program of Supervision for Field Personnel, 1963 (Box 195, Folder 2)
    - Gold Shield Handbook, 1974 (Box 195, Folder 3)
    - GSM Rate Manual, 1991 (Box 195, Folder 4)
    - GSM The Commuter Program, 1993 (Box 195, Folder 5)
    - GSM Process Management Manual, 1993, 1996 (Box 195, Folder 6-7)
    - Sales Awarness, undated (Box 195, Folder 8)
    - GSM Orientation, undated (Box 195, Folder 9)
    - GSM Manual of Information and Instructions, 1941, undated (Box 196)
      Materials include three manuals used by GSM agents. Each manual contains rates covering the Ordinary, Monthly Life, Industrial, and Health and Accident Departments. Materials also include a staff survey.
- Policy Specimens and Certificates of Contribution and Advancement, 1909-1999
  This series includes one hundred years of insurance policy specimens and samples of GSM Certificates of Contribution and Certificates of Advancement.
  - Policy Specimens, 1909-1999 (Box 197, Box 198, Box 199, Box 200, Box 201, Box 202, Box 203, Box 204)
    GSM collected its own policy specimens and samples from other insurance companies.
    Box 197: Bulk is GSM policy specimens but also includes three files of specimens collected by William Nickerson, Jr., and one file by his son Victor Albert Nickerson, which includes the American Mutual Benefit Association Ritual and Revised Constitution as well as his own life insurance policy which lists his mother, Bertha B. Nickerson as beneficiary. Victor Nickerson worked for GSM's field auditing department but left the Company in 1957 to go into business for himself as a real estate broker, appraiser and loan correspondent for GSM. Also included is one file of Winston Mutual policy specimens. Items are dated 1909 to 1961.
    Box 198: Materials include GSM Accident and Health Department policy specimens and samples from The Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Company of New Jersey, Federal Casualty Company of Michigan and Mutual Benefit Health and Accident Association of Omaha. Items are dated 1925 to 1961.
    Box 199: Materials include one book of GSM Accident and Health Department policy specimens with annotations that indicate form numbers, discontinued dates, policy names and states covered. Items are dated 1926, 1934-1954.
    Box 200: Materials include one book of GSM policy specimens with annotations that indicate form numbers, discontinued dates, policy names and states covered. This book is divided into the following sections: Monthly Industrial, Funeral Benefit, Juvenile, Weekly and Ordinary. Items are dated 1932 to 1959.
    Box 201: Materials include GSM policy specimens dated 1938 to 1972.
    Box 202: Materials include GSM policy specimens and samples of life insurance applications and policy envelopes, dated 1952 to 1999.
    Box 203: Three Policy Specimen Books contain copies of all available policies issued by Golden State Mutual since 1925. The issue year and the discontinued year are shown for all policies no longer issued. Only the issue year is shown for currently issued policies. This book was published in January 1969.
    Box 204: Two Policy Specimen Books contain copies of all available Life Policies issued by Golden State Mutual since 1925. The issue year and the discontinued year are shown for all policies no longer issued. Only the issue year is shown for currently issued policies. This book was published in May 1972.
  - Certificates of Contribution, 1933-1939, 1969-1970, 1994 (Box 205, Folder 1-4)
    During the Company's formation, William Nickerson, Jr. sought actuarial advice from John H. Upton at his offices in Burbank. Nickerson explained that he wanted to form an old line legal reserve life insurance company but could not do it on the capital stock plan because it took too much money. They discussed raising money by subscription and Upton suggested using the term Contribution Certificates. There was no law in California for or against securities of this name. Nickerson thought the name "as good as any" and they decided upon the wording of the Contribution Certificates that night. "These Contribution Certificates were to be issued in denominations of $50," wrote Nickerson. According to the Company's definition, "A Certificate of Contribution is an instrument evidencing a contingent promise to repay the original contribution out of corporate earnings. They are not regarded as a commercially salable security."
    Norman O. Houston was responsible for selling the Certificates during the Company's organization efforts. The Company sold Certificates of Contribution again in 1925, 1938, 1940 and 1970. Members of the Board of Directors, Officers, Employees and Policyowners living in the State of California were allowed to purchase Certificates of Contribution. The sale of Certificates of Contribution in 1970 boosted the Company's surplus to more than $3 million for the first time in history.
    In addition to Certificates of Contribution samples, the files include correspondence, applications to the California State Insurance Commissioner to offer and sell Certificates of Contribution and administrative procedures concerning the sales. The 1994 file includes correspondence with the California Department of Insurance and an amended application to issue Certificates of Contribution.
  - Certificates of Advancement, 1933-1944, 1957 (Box 205, Folder 4, Box 206, Box 207, Box 208, Box 209)
    In order to receive its license to operate from the California Department of Insurance, William Nickerson, Jr., George Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston, organizers of the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company, decided to sell Certificates of Advancement to meet the required $15,000 deposit with the state treasurer as a guarantee fund. Norman O. Houston sold Certificates of Advancement which promised liberal interest and gave the Company the right to redeem them whenever its surplus became sufficient. In 1938 the Company initiated its drive to convert its legal status from an assessment company to an old line legal reserve. The conversion meant that the Company had to deposit $250,000 in bonds with the state treasurer. The Golden State Board of Directors elected to employ the sale of Certificates of Advancement again to raise the required deposit.
    Box 205: Materials include correspondence with legal counsel, Walter A. Gordon, Certificate of Advancement Series "A" samples, telegraphs, Board of Directors minutes and resolutions and typed copies of the application to sell Certificates of Advancement. (1933-1939)
    Box 206: Materials include two books of Certificates of Advancement Series "A" signed by two of the following: William Nickerson, Jr., Norman O. Houston, George A. Beavers, Jr. or Edgar J. Johnson. (1939-1944)
    Box 207: Materials include two books of Certificates of Advancement and Contribution Series "B" signed by William Nickerson, Jr. and Norman O. Houston. (1941-1943)
    Box 208: Materials include one book of Certificates of Advancement and Contribution Series "B" signed by two of the following: Norman O. Houston, George A. Beavers, Jr. or Edgar J. Johnson. (1941-1944)
    Box 209: Materials include one book of Certificates of Advancement and Contribution Series "B" signed by two of the following: William Nickerson, Jr., Norman O. Houston, George A. Beavers, Jr. or Edgar J. Johnson and one book of Series "A" and Series "B" redemption lists. (1941-1944, 1957)
- Advertising and Publicity Files, 1923, 1928-2004, 2009
  Materials include scrapbooks, press clippings, calendars, Public Relations Division files, publications files, public relations specimens, posters, advertising files, and audiovisual materials.
  Verna A. Hickman began building Golden State Mutual's public relations department when she was appointed Public Relations Supervisor in 1944. Under Hickman, policyholders became "policyowners" to emphasize the mutual ownership of the Company and the GSM agent was first referred to as "The Man with the Golden Pen."
  Additionally, copies of the calendar had increased from 7,000 in 1926 to an average printing of 175,000 and the 1961 calendar which features a photo of black, white and Asian children at play won the Life Advertisers Association Award of Excellence and was included in the Harvard Business Review as a model of interracial advertising. The aforementioned calendar and the Harvard Review issue may be found in box 217. This image is also featured in GSM's Destination Tomorrow booklet located in box 218.
  GSM also received recognition as the first U.S. corporation to use its initials in its logo. Its logotype of its first three initials on an oval seal was designed in 1951 by Saul Bass, a UCLA professor who became a world famous industrial designer. This logotype and the Company stationery won two first prizes at the 1954 Gilcrafter Letterhead Contest and the Lithographers National Association award in 1955.
  Verna A. Hickman hired artist William E. Pajaud as Art Director in 1957. He designed advertisements, produced and distributed the Company's publications and curated its Afro-American Art Collection. After a few years, Pajaud was promoted to Public Relations and Advertising Manager and then Director of Public Relations, Advertising, Sales Promotion and Corporate Secretary. Pajaud served GSM for thirty years until his retirement in 1987.
  - Scrapbooks, 1930-1941, 1943-1945, 1947-1952, 1960-1963, 1971-1975, 1982-1986
    - Ads, News Releases Scrapbooks, 1930-1939 (Box 210, Box 211)
      Box 210: Materials include advertisements and press clippings that document the Company's first ten years.
      Box 211: Materials include advertisements, ephemera and press clippings which profile GSM as the host of the National Negro Insurance Association Convention in Los Angeles. (1937-1939)
    - Company and Individuals Publicity Scrapbook, 1940 (Box 212, Folder 1)
      Press clippings include articles on Board of Education member Fay E. Allen's charges of racial discrimination in teacher appointments, NAACP drives, the pool opening at the Val Verde County Park, a birthday party for Golden State's cashier Helen E. Hodge, the Company's sole female officer, and the death of William Nickerson, Sr.
    - Ads, News Releases Scrapbooks, 1940-1941, 1943-1945, 1947-1949, 1949-1950 (Box 212, Folder 2, Box 213, Box 214, Box 215)
      Box 212: Scrapbook includes advertisements, press clippings and a Golden State News Bulletin article on the recordkeeping skills of Mrs. Helen E. Hodge who was called as a state witness to verify statements about the organization. (1940-1941)
      Box 213: Three scrapbooks include advertisements, press clippings, William Nickerson, Jr. funeral programs and ephemera such as matchbooks and birthday cards. (1943-1945)
      Box 214: Scrapbook includes advertisements, news releases, programs and bulletins. (1947-1949)
      Box 215: Scrapbook includes advertisements, news releases, souvenir church, concert and theater programs and a full color GSM "In God Is Our Trust" poster in honor of its Los Angeles District employees "Who Answered Our Country's Call to the Colors." (1949-1950)
    - Publicity Scrapbooks, 1949-1952, 1950, 1960-1962 (Box 216, Box 217)
      Box 216: Materials include three Public Relations scrapbooks which contain press clippings concerning the Chamber of Commerce presentation of a 25th Anniversary GSM plaque to President Houston and Chairman Beavers, Home Office Opening commemorative key chain, National Association of Colored Women Incorporated Song Book, Open House Tour Guide Manual and ephemera such as posters, flyers, business card calendars and holiday cards. (1949-1952)
      Box 217: Scrapbook includes copies of the Company's 1961 calendar and Harvard Business Review reprints that reference the calendar images. The bulk of the scrapbook is press clippings from Black newspapers and magazines regarding GSM employees, Directors, Home Office and District Offices. (1960-1962)
    - Public Relations Scrapbooks, circa 1961-1962 (Box 218)
      Folder 1: Scrapbook includes promotional materials for GSM Sales Conferences and All Year Awards such as posters, a 7" record narrated by Vice President A.J. Kelly Williams for the 1961 Mexico City Sales Conference, programs, pamphlets, a souvenir kit and Mexico City incentive postcards from President Norman O. Houston.
      Folder 2: Scrapbook includes a Home Office post card, a murals Christmas card created by the GSM print shop, Junior Sunday School Lessons booklet, calendars, Historical Murals booklet, Church program, "Destination: Tomorrow" education brochure and booklet, Nursery Bible Lessons booklet featuring GSM calendar photo, All Year Awards program, Complete the Picture pamphlets, Community Service flyer, Founder's Month flyers and pamphlets, correspondence from the Pacific Coast Tabernacle #1 of the Knights and Daughters of Tabor, Westminster Neighborhood Association "This Child is Growing up in Watts. How Will He Grow?" pamphlet, Home Office Christmas card, flyer for Twilight Concert featuring J.E. Edwards Gospel, Youth and Children's Choirs of First A.M.E. Church, The Golden Chain of Thought leaflets, The Man With the Golden Pen stationery and Public Relations and Advertising Manager William E. Pajaud's business card.
    - GSM Newspaper Clippings Scrapbook, 1962-1963 (Box 219)
      Scrapbook includes articles which feature the following: Biddy Mason, Marion Anderson, Mary Ellen "Mammy" Pleasant, Sojourner Truth, Mary McLeod Bethune, Ernest Shell, Kelly Williams, Edgar J. Johnson, George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman B. Houston, Norman O. Houston, Byron Beverly, Leo Henderson, the National Insurance Association (NIA) meeting in Los Angeles, Helen E. Batiste, Verna A. Hickman, George A. Beavers, Jr.'s election as NIA President, U.S. Attorney General Robert F. Kennedy congratulating Beavers on his NIA presidency, William E. Pajaud, Lady Allan's Home Office tour, Richard Nixon meeting with the Los Angeles Negro community, Mabel Cleveland, George A. Beavers, Jr. and L.A. Dodger Maury Wills, GSM underwriter Helen S. Love's City Council candidacy and the appointment of Ernest Shell, Willie Baxter and Alma Polk to the Detroit Commission on Community Relations.
    - Public Relations Scrapbooks, 1971-1975, 1982-1986 (Box 220, Box 221, Box 222, Folder 1-2)
      Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically and include advertisements and press clippings.
      Box 220: Scrapbooks include articles on the following: Verna A. Hickman's progressive career, retirements of Norman O. Houston and Edgar J. Johnson, GSM's Negro Art Collection, presentation of 30 year service pins to Jack Jones and Lolette Davis, Bill Cosby's presentation of an autographed basketball to the Jordan High team captain at GSM's City Champions Victory Banquet, GSM and Ford Motor Company's $90,000,000 pact, Chicago District Office cashier Louise M. Bennett's retirement after 33 years of service, L.A. Eastside field representative Christine Frisby's retirement after 20 years of service, President Ivan J. Houston's membership in the Committee of 100, GSM Victory Banquet for title winning Verbum Dei High includes photo of Ivan J. Houston, Willie Davis, Randy Echols and Verbum Dei MVP Raymond Lewis, Westside District Office cashier LeVaughn Wallace receiving her 25 year pin from Ernest Shell and Home Office Director of Data Processing Amanda G. Lockett named assistant secretary. (1970-1975)
      Box 221: Scrapbooks include articles on the following: Bertha B. Nickerson's death, M. Eve Williams and "The Lady with the Golden Pen," Black capitalism, GSM's pact with United Airlines, Golden State Minority Foundation's Medal of Excellence presentation to Secretary of Housing and Urban Development Samuel R. Pierce, Jr., the murder of GSM agent Warren Cassem, The Black Agenda, GSM's Home Office Marketing Administration Manager Bonita Dooley's presentation of a check to Amani Carille of the Friends of the William Grant Still Community Arts Center, GSM's $100 million contract with R.J. Reynolds Industries, Chairman Ivan J. Houston's address to the National African Federated Chamber of Congress, dedication of Norman O. Houston Park, Librarian Miriam Matthews, GSM's receipt of the Black Business Pioneer Award, Golden State Mutual Minority Foundation's presentation of Medal of Excellence to ABC newsman Max Robinson, GSM's involvement with Operation Santa Claus, artist Betye Saar, GSM's contract with McDonald's Corporation, Gladys Owens and her great-grandmother Biddy Mason and Dr. H. Claude Hudson, Mr. Civil Rights. (1972-1984)
      Box 222: Scrapbook includes articles on Black architects, Dr. Thomas Kilgore, the death of Attorney Charles H. Matthews, Ernest Shell's death, the death of L.A.'s first Black Postmaster Leslie Nelson Shaw, GSM's Negro Art Collection, GSM's acquisition of Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company, GSM's 60th Anniversary celebration, former Winston Mutual President George E. Hill, Ivan J. Houston's speech on the status of Black business to the Consolidated Realty Board, GSM's Manager of Public Relations Cheryl Procter's Black Women of Achievement honor, National Newspaper Publishers Association founder John Sengstacke, the death of Mrs. Lola Beavers and the death of attorney Earl B. Dickerson. (1985-1986)
  - Press clippings, 1947-1984
    Files include GSM national press clippings and press releases generated by Verna A. Hickman for Information and Field Services.
    - Press clippings, 1947-1984 (Box 222, Folder 3-6, Box 223, Box 224, Box 225)
      Box 222: Clippings and press releases include stories on the following: GSM's Home Office Opening with Lieutenant Governor Goodwin K. Knight, Norman O. Houston, the GSM Home Office printing press, William Nickerson, Jr. Gardens housing project, Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce honor of GSM's 25th birthday, German labor delegation tour of the Home Office, Verna A. Hickman and Byron Beverly receive GSM employee assembly honors, GSM Comptroller Helen E. Hodge marriage, National Negro Insurance Association meeting in Los Angeles, President Norman O. Houston's car accident and hospitalization, Girls' Day visitors from local high schools meet with GSM women, Founder's Month, GSM groundbreaking ceremonies, the GSM Murals conference and artists' tour of California, construction of Home Office building, brief history of William Nickerson, Jr., brief history of GSM, The Negro in California History murals unveiling, dedication of the William Nickerson, Jr. memorial bust, Miriam Matthews and Titus Alexander's murals research, and special GSM Women's Luncheon with remarks from Comptroller Helen E. Hodge and Board Member Bertha B. Nickerson. (1948-1967)
      Box 223: Clippings include articles on the following: Ralph J. Bunche, the founding and development of GSM, Negro insurance companies and big business, Mme. C.J. Walker, Black insurance companies and Black capitalism, under-insured Black men, great Negroes in history, Titus Alexander bookplate presentation, the Negro in California, James Cleveland Owens Lucky Strike advertisement, the Wilfandel Club and a Los Angeles Public Library anti-prejudice art show. (1947-1971)
      Box 224: Clippings and press releases include stories on the following: Chicago office's 16th anniversary, the opening of GSM's new West Side office located at 1 North Western Avenue in Chicago, Norman O. Houston's support for Georgiana Hardy's election to the Board of Education, GSM opening a Women's Army Corps and Air Force Recruiting station in its Home Office lobby, City Housing Authority Commissioner George A. Beavers, Jr. speaks out against opponents of public housing, GSM gains $8.5 million in life insurance in force, Toscanini Baton unveiling at the Home Office, the death of George A. Beavers, Sr., City Housing Authority's hearings on communist infiltration, Sentinel editor and publisher Leon H. Washington pickets Sentinel for what the Eagle called "anti-Negro thinking," Nickersonian affair at the Wilfandel Club, George Washington Carver national monument dedication, opening of Interracial Texas-American Insurance Company, Chicago office Supervising Cashier Louise Bennett, rioters attack Negro family in Trumball Park housing project, Booker T. Washington cigars, Home Economist and GSM Cafeteria Operator Theresa M. Boswell, GSM employee song contest and GSM's participation in the Los Angeles Board of Education's cooperative guidance workshop business program. (1950-1953)